Natalia Sozontova

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Software Developer Engineer in Test with years of hands-on experience in performing manual/automated testing, and Regression Testing of Web-Based Applications. Extensive background using Maven build tool, Selenium automation frameworks, Jenkins and TestNG. Strong knowledge of agile methodology, waterfall model and involvement in all phases of Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) and Software Testing Life Cycle (STLC).

CLEARANCE: U.S. Citizen, clearable

CERTIFICATIONS:

- Certified Trusted Tester for Web on Windows
- Oracle Certified Associate
- Professional Scrum Master
- Cisco Certified Network Associate

EDUCATION:

Immanuel Kant Baltic Federal University
Master's degree in Engineering and Technology

WORK EXPERIENCE

December 2019 to Present OneGlobe LLC - Herndon, VA SDET/Test Automation engineer

- Involved in analyzing application specifications, design, developing and executing test cases for Manual and Automated testing.
- Designed, built and maintained User Stories based test automation scripts for UI validation using Cucumber, Selenium WebDriver, Java, JUnit, Maven
- Logged defects, monitored their status and tracked them to closure using Jira with Xray plug-in.
- Updated an existing automation testing framework to adapt with API data staging involving multiple microservices and Camunda workflow.
- Used GitHub and Bitbucket as version control tools.
- Retrieved testing data on AWS by setting correct queries request against Dynamic DB.
- Performed backend manual testing by executing queries against multiple environments for PostgreSQL DB.
- Wrote automated test script for front end using Selenium, Cucumber and back end using Rest Assured Libraries testing.
- Hold KT sessions with multiple testing teams to share the knowledge about the project, users, generating testing data.

Environment: Java, Selenium WebDriver, JUnit, Git, GitHub, Bitbucket, Jenkins, Cucumber, Maven, Jira Xray, Gherkin, Eclipse, D Postman, Rest-Assured, pgAdmin, Camunda, Dynamic DB, AWS, PostgreSQL DB.

September 2017 to October 2019 Navy Federal Credit Union - Vienna, VA SDET/Test Automation engineer

- Involved in analyzing application specifications, design, developing and executing test cases for Manual and Automated testing.
- Designed, built and maintained User Stories based test automation scripts for UI validation using Cucumber, Selenium WebDriver, Java, JUnit, Maven through business, functional and technical expertise.
- Logged defects, monitored their status and tracked them to closure using Jira with Xray plug-in.
- Followed Agile-Scrum methodology as part of SDLC.
- Participated in all Agile ceremonies during the Sprint, such as Product Backlog Grooming meeting, Sprint Planning meeting, Daily Stand-up meeting, Sprint Demo/Review meeting and Sprint Retrospective meeting.
- Performed functional testing, smoke testing, and regression testing.
- Involved in the Design and implementation of Hybrid Automation framework supporting Behavioral Driven Development (BDD), Data-Driven Development (DDD) and Page Object Model (POM) for Selenium automation using Selenium WebDriver, Cucumber, Java, Maven, and JUnit.
- Modified and executed Test Case Scripts (Java Selenium WebDriver) in IntelliJ IDEA IDE.
- Designed object repository in the Selenium framework using CSS, XPATH, and other locators.
- Experienced in handling Alerts, Frames, and Pop-ups in Selenium.
- Performed Selenium Data-Driven tests by using Apache POI in order to get the test data from Excel sheets.
- Handled Selenium WebDriver features such as Implicit wait and Explicit wait under synchronization.
- Maintained Java and Selenium test source code and resources in the GIT version control tool.
- Implemented Continuous Integration of the code using Jenkins.
- Performed Database/Back-End testing by writing SQL Queries for data validation testing and established JDBC connection using Java programming language.
- Involved in API manual testing using Postman and automation testing using REST Assured by writing code to send request and validate JSON response.
- Maintained BDD (Behavior Driven Development) using Cucumber Features, Scenarios and Step Definitions in Gherkin language.

Environment: Java, Selenium WebDriver, JUnit, Git, GitHub, Jenkins, Cucumber, Maven, Apache POI, Jira Xray, Gherkin, IntelliJ IDEA, DDD, BDD, POM, Agile Scrum, Excel, Apache POI, Postman, Rest-Assured, JDBC, SQL Developer, Oracle Database.

June 2015 to September 2017 CareFirst BlueCross BlueShield - Reston, VA SDET/Test Automation Engineer

- Worked in an Agile environment with frequently changing requirements and features set.
- Worked on the Functional, Smoke and Regression tests.
- Implemented Page Object Model Pattern automation testing framework utilizing Java, TestNG and Selenium WebDriver.
- Supported smoke and regression testing in a production environment during deployments.
- Managed the framework dependency jars using Maven.
- Integrated with Continuous Integration tool Jenkins for running test on nightly basis automatically.
- Performed different browser testing (Firefox, Chrome) using Selenium WebDriver and Java.
- Used Jira as a project tracking tool, Defect Tracking, and Test case Management tool.
- Involved in the automation of test cases using Selenium WebDriver, Java, TestNG and Maven.
- Used Eclipse IDE analyzed, debugged Java code and performed Black Box Testing.
- Using GitHub to maintain and manage the Java scripts.
- Involved in Defect tracking, reporting until the defects are resolved.

- Performed Automation testing using Selenium on Web-based (Browser) application.
- Developed automation scripts, execution, and analysis of test results using POM framework in Selenium.
- Wrote CSS Selectors, XPath expressions to identify web elements.

Environment: Selenium WebDriver, Java, Maven, TestNG, Eclipse, Jira, Jenkins, Postman, Excel, GIT, GitHub, POM, Agile, Apache POI.

May 2013 to June 2015

Alarm.com - Tysons Corner, VA

QA Tester

- Identified test scenarios from business requirements to perform Manual Testing.
- Reviewed project documentation and worked closely with Business Analyst (BA), Product Owner (PO), and Development for creating Test Cases.
- Performed GUI testing manually to check the application behavior on different browsers such as Chrome, Firefox.
- Reviewed and updated Requirements Traceability Matrix (RTM) to ensure all requirements are covered.
- Linked requirements to tests and defects, as well as analyzed and tested defects.
- Reviewed the scripts developed by Automation Test Engineers and QA testers.
- Documented test results and reported defects through Jira.
- Communicated with the development team on defect reporting and resolution.

Environment: Waterfall, Windows, Jira, MS Office, Chrome and Firefox browsers.

April 2010 to May 2013

Katauri Interactive - Kaliningrad, RU

QA Tester

- Delivered **test** scenarios from business requirements to perform manual testing.
- Performed manually testing to check the application behavior.
- Reviewed project documentation and closely worked with Development team for creating Test Cases.
- Created defect reporting and resolution.

Environment: Waterfall, Windows, MS Office, Excel.

TECHNICAL SKILLS:

Certifications	Oracle Certified Associate (OCA), Professional Scrum Master I (PSM I), Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA), Network Engineering/Specialist (Career Studies Certificate), 508 Certified Tester
Automation Testing Tools	Java, Selenium WebDriver, Cucumber, Jenkins, TestNG, JUnit, Apache POI, JDBC, SQL

	Developer
Database	Oracle, MongoDb, DynamoDb, PostgreSQL, Mongoose, Sequelize
Languages	Java, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, SQL, Gherkin
Project Building Tools	Maven
IDE	Eclipse, IntelliJ IDEA
Test Management/Defect Tracking Tool	Jira/Xray
Version Control System	GIT
API Testing	POSTMAN, REST-Assured, Camunda
Testing Frameworks	DDD, BDD, POM
Operating System	Windows, macOS
Methodologies	Agile/Scrum, Waterfall
Development	NodeJS, ReactJS, Express